In many occasions, you won't want to end the loop before it's supposed to.
很多情况下 你可能想在循环正常结束之前就让它停止
Let's have a look at an example.
我们来看一个案例
Imagine you writing a program that controls
想象你在写一个程序
your smartphone to search for Wi-Fi networks around you.
该程序会控制你的智能手机来搜寻附近的 Wi-Fi 网络
You want to retry 10 times and then give up.
你想重试十次 然后停止搜寻
So we build a loop that starts I from one all the way until 10 and increment by one.
所以我们创建了一个循环 i 从 1 开始计数 一直到 10 每次增量为 1
So this is going to repeat whatever's inside that loop exactly 10 times.
所以循环里无论有什么指令 都会整整重复执行 10 次
Inside our for loop,
在循环里
we will be calling this function,
我们调用这个函数
which is called check Wi-Fi.
叫做 checkWifi
Imagine that this function actually performs as
假设这个函数实现时会进行一次 Wi-Fi 查找
a Wi-Fi search and returns true if it actually found one.
如果找到了一个 Wi-Fi 函数就会返回真值
So, we're going to assign the return value from
所以我们要将这个函数的返回值赋给这里的布尔
this function into our Boolean here which we called Wi-Fi available.
该布尔叫做 wifiAvailable
Which means that if this Boolean is true,
也就是说 如果这个布尔值为真
then we've successfully found a Wi-Fi network.
那就意味着我们成功地找到了一个 Wi-Fi 网络
If it's false, we still haven't found anything, and we keep trying.
如果为假 那就还没找到 得继续找
Right after that, we just add this If condition and check if that variable is true.
在这之后 我们加上这么个 if 条件 判断这个变量是否为真
If it is, then we just simply print out Wi-Fi found and that's it.
如果是 那就输出 Wifi found 函数结束
If it's not true,
如果不是
then we keep looping inside our for loop for the 10 times that we want it to.
那就继续在 for 循环里循环 按我们设想的那样循环十次
This we'll keep retrying 10 times until it either finds it or not.
这段代码会重复十次 直到找到了网络或者十次都找不到
This looks really perfect,
看起来很棒了
except for one weird scenario where say
除非发生一个奇怪的情景
that we actually find a Wi-Fi network in the middle of our loop.
如果我们在循环尚未结束时就找到了 Wi-Fi 网络
Say it iteration number five.
假设是第五次迭代
So, imagine that iteration number five,
想象在第五次迭代的时候
our check Wi-Fi happened to return true.
我们的 checkWifi 函数返回了真值
Updating our variable here to become true.
使变量更新为真
So we step inside our If condition here and we print out Wi-Fi found.
于是我们进入这里的 if 条件 输出 Wifi found
We end our IF condition,
之后 if 条件就结束了
and we're still inside the loop.
但我们还在循环里
So we go back up, we increment I making it six and six is still less than or equal to 10.
于是我们回到这上面来 给 i 增量 使其变为 6 而 6 仍小于或等于 10
So we go back in here again and we check Wi-Fi again,
于是再进入这里 再检查 Wi-Fi
which if we're still in range,
如果我们还在网络范围内
will also return true so that will actually print out Wi-Fi found again.
这个函数还是会返回真值 因而 Wifi found 这条信息会再次输出
In fact, it will keep printing out Wi-Fi
事实上 这里的 for 循环在剩下的迭代中
for the remaining iterations in our for loop here.
还会不断地输出 Wifi 提示
This doesn't seem exactly like what we expected to do.
这并不完全符合我们的设想
The way I would have imagined it is that once we find a Wi-Fi network,
我想象的是 一旦我们找到一个 Wi-Fi 网络
we want to end this search.
就结束这次查找
Luckily, Java offers this keyword called break.
好在 Java 提供了关键字 break
If we simply add break keyword here,
我们只需把关键字 break 加到这里
what we're saying is once we actually find a Wi-Fi and printout Wi-Fi found,
这样一旦找到了一个 Wi-Fi 并输出了信息 Wifi found
break would actually exit this for loop entirely.
break 就会彻底跳出这个 for 循环
So it will not continue looping no matter whether this condition is still true or not.
所以无论条件是真还是假 循环都不会继续了
This is very handy in so many situations that we are going to run into.
有了这个 我们将来遇到的很多情况都能迎刃而解了
In fact, it also works with while loops.
事实上 break 也适用于 while 循环
Let's have a look at an example there.
我们来看一个案例
Imagine that you're playing this game where
想象你在玩一个游戏
the goal is to roll a dice until you get a six.
你得把一个骰子掷出六点
However, if you get a three then you lose.
但如果掷出的是三点 你就输了
So we're going to implement a function that keeps rolling a dice until you get a six.
所以我们要实现这么个函数 一直掷骰子直到掷出六点
If you get a six, then you win,
如果掷出六点 你就赢了
but if you get a three, you lose.
但如果掷出三点 你就输了
Our function would return a Boolean which is true if I won or false if I didn't win.
函数将返回一个布尔值 如果我赢了的话 值为真 如果没有赢 值为假
We'll just call it roll a six.
我们就管它叫 rollASix 吧
It doesn't take any parameters.
该函数不接受任何参数
Inside, we'll simply roll the dice using
在里面 我们只需用 rollDice 函数来掷骰子
the roll dice function and store that into an integer variable called dice,
并将结果赋值给整数变量 dice
and we'll follow it with our while loop.
然后用 while 循环来执行这个过程
While dice is not equal to six, keep rolling.
当 dice 不等于 6 时 继续掷骰子
Perfect. So, this while loop would keep rolling our dice until we eventually get a six.
完美 这个 while 循环会一直掷骰子 直到掷出六点
However, we need to check if the dice ever got a three.
不过 我们需要判断骰子掷出的是不是三点
So we add this if condition,
所以我们加上这个 if 条件
if dice equals equals three, then we break.
如果 dice 等于 3 我们就 break
Break here means that we're going to break outside this while loop.
这里 break 的意思就是 我们要跳出这个 while 循环
We're not going to keep trying,
不会再掷骰子了
we're not going to keep looping inside the while loop.
不会再执行 while 循环里的语句了
It's over. We've lost.
循环彻底结束了 我们输了
However, if you noticed,
不过 不知你是否注意到了
whether we actually get a six or a three in both cases,
无论我们掷出了六点还是三点
we're just going to end up at this part here.
都只会到达这里
We're not going to be able to tell whether we
函数停止后 我们无法得知
actually got a six or a three at that point.
自己掷出的是六点还是三点
So to be able to decide whether we actually won or not,
所以要知道赢了还是没赢
we're just going to add another If condition down here.
我们需要在这再加一个 if 条件
If the dice is equal to six,
如果 dice 等于 6
then we're going to return true,
我们就返回真值
else, we're going to return false.
否则就返回假值
So if this while loop kept retrying
这样一来 待 while 循环不断掷骰子
until it eventually got a six and then we got to this phase here,
掷出了六点后 我们就会到达这个阶段
so we just checked that the dice is actually a six, then we return true.
检查 dice 是否真的为 6 然后返回真值
If the dice however happened to have a three in the middle of our retries here,
如果重掷期间 dice 刚好变成 3
then we're going to break out the loop ending
那我们就会跳出循环到这里
here and we're going to do this if condition and it's not six.
进行 if 条件判断 因为不等于 6
So it's going to go to the else and it's going to return a false.
所以就是其它情况 因此返回出假值
Perfect. So we can see how handy break is even with the while loops.
完美 综上我们可以看出 就算是用于 while 循环 break 也很方便
Now, let's have a look at an example where you are going to
现在 我们来看一个案例
use the break keyword to solve a problem.
你得用关键字 break 来解决一个问题